У попередньому відео я
systems of equations, and I sort of brushed
говорив про лінійне 00:00:15,800
aside the discussion of actually computing
solutions to these systems.
--&gt; 00:00:19,690 3
And while it’s true that number-crunching
is something we typically leave to the computers,
є хорошим лакмусовим папірцем
digging into some of these computational methods
для того, чи
дійсно ви розумієте, що
this is really where the rubber meets the
відбувається, оскільки 00:00:31,680
road.
--&gt; 00:00:32,680 00:00:32,680 --&gt;
Here I want to describe the geometry behind
a certain method for computing solutions to
00:00:36,379 8 9
these systems, known as Cramer’s rule.
обов’язково подивіться відповідні відео
The relevant background needed here is an
understanding of determinants, dot products,
на ці теми,
and of linear systems of equations, so be
якщо ви не знайомі
або не знаєте.
Але спочатку!
Попередньо я повинен
is not the best way for computing solutions
сказати, що правило
to linear systems of equations.
Крамера 00:00:56,379 --&gt;
Gaussian elimination, for example, will always
be faster.
00:00:58,010 00:00:58,010
So why learn it?
--&gt; 00:01:01,950 16
Think of this as a sort of cultural excursion;
it’s a helpful exercise in deepening your
17 допомагає консолідувати
knowledge of the theory of these systems.
ідеї лінійної
Wrapping your mind around this concept will
алгебри, такі як
детермінанти та лінійні
seeing how they relate to each other.
системи, by
Also, from a purely artistic standpoint, the
ultimate result is just really pretty to think
00:01:19,960 --&gt; 00:01:24,619
about, much more so that Gaussian elimination.
22 23 працюватимуть
Alright, so the setup here will be some linear
system of equations, say with two unknowns,
системи з
x and y, and two equations.
більшою кількістю невідомих
In principle, everything we’re talking about
і такою ж
кількістю рівнянь.
Але для простоти
to hold in our heads.
менший приклад
So as I talked about in a previous video,
you can think of this setup geometrically
кращий 00:01:46,349
as a certain known matrix transforming an
unknown vector, [x; y], where you know what
--&gt; 00:01:50,599
the output is going to be, in this case [-4;
29 -2].
Пам’ятайте, що стовпці цієї
you how the matrix acts as a transform, each
матриці повідомляють 00:02:06,250
one telling you where the basis vectors of
the input space land.
--&gt; 00:02:10,899 33
So this is a sort of puzzle, what input [x;
y], is going to give you this
тип відповіді, яку ви
output [-4; -2]?
тут отримаєте, може
Remember, the
залежати від того,
чи перетворення хлюпає
all of space into a lower dimension.
чи ні 00:02:44,299 --&gt;
That is if it has zero determinant.
00:02:46,080 00:02:46,080 --&gt;
In that case, either none of the inputs land
on our given output or there are a whole bunch
00:02:51,849 39 40
of inputs landing on that output.
повний n-вимірний простір, у
But for this video we’ll limit our view
to the case of a non-zero determinant, meaning
якому він почався;
the output of this transformation still spans
кожен вхід потрапляє
на один і
and every output has one and only one input.
тільки один вихід 00:03:12,549
One way to think about our puzzle is that
we know the given output vector is some linear
--&gt; 00:03:14,840 44
combination of the columns of the matrix;
x*(the vector where i-hat lands) + y*(the
обчислити, що таке
vector where j-hat lands), but we wish to
x і y.
Для початку дозвольте
is wrong, but in the right direction.
мені показати ідею,
The x-coordinate of this mystery input vector
is what you get by taking its dot product
що 00:03:18,829
with the first basis vector, [1; 0].
--&gt; 00:03:23,340 48
Likewise, the y-coordinate is what you get
by dotting it with the second basis vector,
49 скалярний
[0; 1].
добуток із трансформованою
So maybe you hope that after the transformation,
версією таємничого
вектора з трансформованим
versions of the basis vectors will also be
00:03:41,939 --&gt; 00:
these coordinates x and y.
03:43,590 00:03:43,590
That’d be fantastic because we know the
transformed versions of each of these vectors.
--&gt; 00:03:50,400 55
There’s just one problem with this: it’s
not at all true!
до і
For most linear transformations, the dot product
після трансформації будуть
дуже різними.
Наприклад, у вас може
pointing in the same direction, with a positive
бути два вектори,
dot product, which get pulled away from each
other during the transformation, in such a
які зазвичай 00:04:04,959
way that they then have a negative dot product.
--&gt; 00:04:09,270 60
Likewise, if things start off perpendicular,
with dot product zero, like the two basis
61 залишатимуться перпендикулярними
vectors, there’s no guarantee that they
після перетворення, зберігаючи
нульовий скалярний добуток.
У прикладі, який
certainly aren’t preserved.
ми розглядали, скалярний
They tend to get bigger since most vectors
are getting stretched.
добуток 00:04:27,140 --&gt;
In fact, transformations which do preserve
dot products are special enough to have their
00:04:30,950 66
own name: Orthonormal transformations.
векторів, перпендикулярних один
These are the ones which leave all the basis
до одного з
одиничною довжиною.
Ви часто думаєте про це як про матриці обертання.
Відповідає жорсткому руху, без
squishing or morphing.
розтягування, 00:04:53,000 --&gt;
Solving a linear system with an orthonormal
matrix is very easy: Since dot products are
00:04:58,920 73 добутку
preserved, taking the dot product between
the output vector and all the columns of your
між вхідним вектором
matrix will be the same as taking the dot
і всіма базисними векторами,
що те саме,
the coordinates of the input vector.
що знайти 00:05:13,599
So, in that very special case, x would be
the dot product of the first column with the
--&gt; 00 :05:18,690
output vector, and y would be the dot product
of the second column with the output vector.
77 найбільш лінійних систем,
Now, even though this idea breaks down for
це вказує нам
у напрямку чогось
geometric understanding for the coordinates
шукати: чи є
of our input vector which remains unchanged
after the transformation?
альтернативний 00:05:37,780 --&gt; 00:05:42,780
If your mind has been mulling over determinants,
you might think of this clever idea: Take
81 вектор, i-hat
the parallelogram defined by the first basis
і таємничий вхідний
вектор [x; y].
Площа цього паралелограма є
1, times the height perpendicular to that
його основою, 00:05:59,990 --&gt;
base, which is the y-coordinate of our input
vector.
00:06:03,460 86, якщо
So, the area of this parallelogram is sort
of a screwy roundabout way to describe the
говорити про координати, але
vector’s y-coordinate; it’s a wacky way
біжимо зі мною.
Насправді, щоб бути більш
think of the signed area of this parallelogram,
точним, ви повинні
in the sense described by the determinant
video.
00:06:19,690 --&gt; 00:06:22,440
That way, a vector with negative y-coordinate
would correspond to a negative area for this
90 подивитися на
parallelogram.
паралелограм, натягнутий на вектор
Symmetrically, if you
і другий базисний
вектор, j-hat, його
will be the x-coordinate of the vector.
площу 00:06:45,099 --
Again, it’s a strange way to represent the
x-coordinate, but you’ll see what it buys
&gt; 00:06:49,370 95 96
us in a moment.
означало б взяти
Here’s what this would look like in three-dimensions:
Ordinarily the way you might think of one
його скалярний добуток
of a vector’s coordinate, say its z-coordinate,
із третім стандартним
базисним вектором, k-hat.
Але замість цього
creates with the other two basis vectors,
розглянемо паралелепіпед, 00:07:11,870
i-hat and j-hat.
--&gt; 00:07:13,569
If you think of the square with area 1 spanned
by i-hat and j-hat as the base of this guy,
00:07:13,569 --&gt; 00:07:20,030
its volume is the same its height, which is
the third coordinate of our vector.
102 інша
Likewise, the wacky way to think about any
координата цього вектора
утворює паралелепіпед між
all the basis vectors other than the one you’re
цим вектором
looking for, and get its volume.
і 00: 07:34,950
Or, rather, we should talk about the signed
volume of these parallelepipeds, in the sense
--&gt; 00:07:37,900
described in the determinant video, where
the order in which you list the three vectors
00:07:37,900 --&gt; 00:07:42,490
matters and you’re using the right-hand
107 правило.
Таким чином негативні координати все ще мають сенс.
Гаразд, навіщо думати
and volumes like this?
про координати
As you apply some matrix transformation, the
areas of the parallelograms don’t stay the
як про
same, they may get scaled up or down.
площі 00:07:56,000 --&gt;
But(!), and this is a key idea of determinants,
all these areas get scaled by the same amount.
00:08:02,039 112
Namely, the determinant of our transformation
113 матриці.
Наприклад, якщо ви
spanned by the vector where your first basis
подивіться на
vector lands, which is the first column of
the matrix, and the transformed version of
паралелограм 00:08:17,850
[x; y], what is its area?
--&gt; 00:08:22,850
Well, this is the transformed version of that
parallelogram we were looking at earlier,
117 118
whose area was the y-coordinate of the mystery
вхідний вектор.
Тож його площа
transformation multiplied by that value.
буде визначником
So, the y-coordinate of our mystery input
vector is the area of this parallelogram,
00:08:39,080 --&gt; 00:08:44,590
spanned by the first column of the matrix
and the output vector, divided by the determinant
122 таємничих
of the full transformation.
вхідних векторів, у
And how do you get this area?
цьому й
Well, we know the coordinates for where the
полягає суть лінійної
системи рівнянь.
Отже, створивши матрицю, перший
the same as that of our matrix, and whose
стовпець якої 00:09:05,670
second column is the output vector, and take
its determinant.
--&gt; 00:09:11,250 129
So look at that; just using data from the
output of the transformation, namely the columns
вектор, ми можемо
of the matrix and the coordinates of our output
відновити y-координату нашого
таємничого вхідного вектора.
Так само ця сама ідея може отримати координату x.
Подивіться на той паралелограм,
which encodes the x-coordinate of the mystery
який ми визначили
input vector, spanned by the input vector
and j-hat.
раніше 00:09:32,580 --&gt;
The transformed version of this guy is spanned
by the output vector and the second column
00:09:36,420 135 помножений
of the matrix, and its area will have been
на визначник матриці.
Отже, координата x нашого
is this area divided by the determinant of
таємничого вхідного вектора 00:09:52,000
the transformation.
--&gt; 00:09:53,980 00:09:53,980
Symmetric to what we did before, you can compute
the area of that output parallelogram by creating
--&gt; 00:09:58,900 140 простору,
a new matrix whose first column is the output
vector, and whose second column is the same
чисел, які ми
as the original matrix.
бачимо в нашій оригінальній
So again, just using data from the output
лінійній системі, ми
можна відновити координату x
of our mystery input vector.
00:10:13,600 --&gt; 00:10:18,440 145
This formula for finding the solutions to
a linear system of equations is known as Cramer’s
146 це 4+2,
rule.
що дорівнює 6, а
Here, just to sanity check ourselves, plug
in the numbers here.
нижній визначник дорівнює
The determinant of that top altered matrix
2, тому координата x
має бути 3.
І справді, озираючись на
we started with, it’s x-coordinate is 3.
цей вхідний вектор
Likewise, Cramer’s rule suggests the y-coordinate
should be 4/2, or 2, and that is indeed the
00:10:35,910 --&gt; 00:10:43,850 151,
y-coordinate of the input vector we started
with here.
і я настійно
The case with three dimensions is similar,
рекомендую вам зупинитися, щоб
подумати над цим.
Ось, я дам вам трохи імпульсу.
У нас є
a 3x3 matrix, and a known output vector, given
це відоме перетворення,
by the right side of our linear system, and
we want to know what input vector lands on
задане 00:11:02,780 --&gt;
this output vector.
00:11:07,580 157 158
If you think of, say, the z-coordinate of
the input vector as the volume of this parallelepiped
вектором, що станеться
spanned by i-hat, j-hat, and the mystery input
з об&#39;ємом цього
паралелепіпеда після перетворення?
Як ви можете обчислити цей новий обсяг?
Дійсно, зробіть паузу
the details of generalizing this to higher
та обдумайте 00:11:32,200
dimensions; finding an expression for each
coordinate of the solution to larger linear
--&gt; 00:11:37,330
systems.
164 165 якийсь
Thinking through more general cases and convincing
yourself that it works is where all the learning
чувак на
will happen, much more so than listening to
YouTube ще раз
пройде міркування.